When most people think about the beginnings
عندما يفكر معظم الناس حول بدايات
of AIDS, they're gonna think back to the 1980s.
الإيدز، سيرجعون بتفكيرهم إلى الثمانينات
And certainly, this was the decade in which we discovered AIDS
وبالتأكيد، فهو العقد الذي اكتشفنا فيه الإيدز
and the virus that causes it, HIV.
والفيروس المسبب له، HIV (فايروس نقص المناعة البشرية)
But in fact this virus crossed over into humans many decades before,
ولكن في الواقع هذا الفيروس انتقل إلى البشر قبل عدة عقود،
from chimpanzees, where the virus originated, into humans who hunt these apes.
من الشمبانزي، حيث نشأ الفيروس، إلى البشر الذين يصطادون القرود.
This photo was taken before the Great Depression
لقد التقطت هذه الصورة قبل الكساد الكبير
in Brazzaville, Congo.
في برازافيل، الكونغو.
At this time, there were thousands of individuals,
في هذا الوقت، كان هناك الآلاف من الأشخاص،
we think, that were infected with HIV.
في اعتقادنا، كانوا مصابين بفيروس HIV
So I have a couple of really important questions for you.
لذلك لدي بعض من الأسئلة المهمة لكم.
If this virus was in thousands
اذا كان آالاف الأشخاص مصابين بهذا
of individuals at this point,
الفايروس في هذه المرحلة،
why was it the case that it took us until 1984
لماذا استغرقنا حتى عام 1984
to be able to discover this virus?
لنكون قادرين على اكتشاف الفيروس؟
OK now, more importantly,
حسنا الآن، والأهم من ذلك،
had we been there in the '40s and '50s, '60s,
هل كنا متواجدين في الأربعينات والخمسينات، والستينات
had we seen this disease, had we understood
هل رأينا هذا المرض، هل فهمنا
exactly what was going on with it, how might that have changed and completely
بالضبط ما كان يحدث معه، وكيف يمكن أن يكون قد تغير
transformed the nature of the way this pandemic moved?
وتحولت طبيعة انتقال هذا الوباء تماما؟
In fact, this is not unique to HIV. The vast majority of
في الواقع، هذا ليس بفريد على فيروس HIV. الغالبية العظمى من
viruses come from animals.
الفيروسات تأتي من الحيوانات.
And you can kind of think of this as a pyramid of this bubbling up of viruses
وكما يمكنكم اعتبار هذا على أنه هرم مليء بالفيروسات
from animals into human populations.
من الحيوانات إلى البشر.
But only at the very top of this pyramid do these things become completely human.
ولكن فقط في أعلى هذا الهرم تصبح تلك الأشياء بشرية تماما.
Nevertheless, we spend the vast majority
ومع ذلك، فإننا نستهلك معظم
of our energy focused on this level of the pyramid,
طاقتنا في التركيز على هذا المستوى من الهرم،
trying to tackle things that are already completely adapted to human beings,
في محاولة لمعالجة الأمور التي تكيفت تماما مع البشر،
that are going to be very very difficult to address --
التي سيكون من الصعب جدا معالجتها -
as we've seen in the case of HIV.
كما شاهدنا في حالة فيروس HIV
So during the last 15 years,
خلال السنوات ال 15 الماضية ،
I've been working to actually study the earlier interface here --
كنت أعمل على دراسة الواجهة الأولية هنا -
what I've labeled "viral chatter," which was a term coined
كما سميته "الإحتكاك الفيروسي"، وهو مصطلح اخترعه
by my mentor Don Burke.
موجهي دون بورك
This is the idea that we can study the sort of
هذه هي فكرة أن نتمكن من دراسة هذا النوع من
pinging of these viruses into human populations,
الأزيز من هذه الفيروسات إلى البشر،
the movement of these agents over into humans;
حركة هؤلاء الوسطاء إلى البشر،
and by capturing this moment,
وعن طريق تجميد هذه اللحظة،
we might be able to move to a situation where we can catch them early.
قد نكون قادرين على الانتقال إلى حالة حيث يمكننا الامساك بهم في وقت مبكر.
OK, so this is a picture, and I'm going to show you
حسنا، هذه هي الصورة، وسوف أريكم
some pictures now from the field.
بعض الصور الآن من الميدان.
This is a picture of a central African hunter.
هذه هي صورة لصياد في وسط افريقيا.
It's actually a fairly common picture.
وهي في الواقع صورة شائعة.
One of the things I want you to note from it
واحد من الأشياء التي أريدكم أن تلاحظوا منها
is blood -- that you see a tremendous amount of blood contact.
هو الدم - ترون قدرا هائلا من الاتصال بالدم
This was absolutely key for us. This is a
وكان هذا هو المفتاح بالنسبة لنا بالتأكيد. وهو
very intimate form of connection.
شكل حميم جدا من الاتصال.
So if we're going to study viral chatter, we need to
أذا كنا نريد دراسة الإحتكاك الفيروسي، علينا
get to these populations who have intensive contact with wild animals.
الوصول إلى هؤلاء السكان الذين هم على اتصال مكثف مع الحيوانات البرية.
And so we've been studying people like this individual.
وهكذا كنا ندرس حالات مثل هذا الشخص.
We collect blood from them, other specimens.
نجمع الدم منهم، عينات أخرى.
We look at the diseases, which are in the animals as well as the humans.
ننظر إلى الأمراض، والتي هي في الحيوانات فضلا عن البشر.
And ideally, this is going to allow us to catch these things
وبشكل مثالي، سيسمح لنا هذا بالإمساك بتلك الأشياء
early on, as they're moving over into human populations.
في وقت مبكر، في أثناء انتقالهم إلى البشر.
And the basic objective of this work is not to just
والهدف الأساسي من هذا العمل ليس فقط
go out once and look at these individuals,
الذهاب إلى هناك وإلقاء نظرة على هؤلاء الأشخاص،
but to establish thousands of individuals
ولكن لوضع آلاف الأشخاص
in these populations that we would monitor
في هذه المجتمعات تحت مراقبة
continuously on a regular basis.
مستمرة على أساس منتظم.
When they were sick, we would collect specimens from them.
عندما يمرضون، فإننا نجمع العينات منهم.
We would actually enlist them --
ونقوم بحشدهم في الواقع -
which we've done now -- to collect specimens from animals.
كما فعلنا هنا - لنجمع عينات من الحيوانات.
We give them these little pieces of filter paper.
نعطيهم أوراق الترشيح الصغيرة.
When they sample from animals,
عندما يأخذون العينات من الحيوانات،
they collect the blood on the filter paper
يجمعون الدم على ورقة الترشيح
and this allows us to identify yet-unknown viruses from exactly the right animals --
وهذا يتيح لنا التعرف على الفيروسات الغير معروفة حتى الآن من الحيوانات المناسبة تماما
the ones that are actually being hunted.
تلك التي هي في الواقع يجري اصطيادها.
(Video) Narrator: Deep in a remote region of Cameroon,
(فيديو): في منطقة نائية بعيدة في الكاميرون،
two hunters stalk their prey.
اثنان من الصيادين يطاردون فريستهم.
Their names are Patrice and Patee.
اسماؤهم هي باتريس وباتي.
They're searching for bush meat;
إنهم يبحثون عن لحوم الطرائد -
forest animals they can kill to feed their families.
حيوانات الغابات يمكن أن تقتل لإطعام عائلاتها.
Patrice and Patee set out most days to go out hunting
يقضي باتريس وباتي معظم أيام الأسبوع للخروج للصيد
in the forest around their homes.
في الغابات وحول منازلهم.
They have a series of traps, of snares that they've set up
لديهم سلسلة من الأفخاخ التي نصبوها
to catch wild pigs, snakes, monkeys,
لصيد الخنازير البرية، والثعابين والقرود
rodents -- anything they can, really.
القوارض، كل ما يمكنهم صيده، حقاً
Patrice and Patee have been out for hours but found nothing.
أمضى باريس وباتي ساعات في الخارج ولكن لم يجدوا شيئاً.
The animals are simply gone.
اختفت الحيوانات ببساطة.
We stop for a drink of water.
نتوقف لشرب الماء.
Then there is a rustle in the brush.
ثم نسمع حفيف الأشجار.
A group of hunters approach,
تتقدم مجموعة من الصيادين.
their packs loaded with wild game.
الأمتعة مليئة بالألعاب البرية.
There's at least three viruses
هناك ما لا يقل عن ثلاثة فيروسات
that you know about, which are in this particular monkey.
تعلم بوجودها في هذا القرد بالتحديد.
Nathan Wolfe: This species, yeah. And there's many many more pathogens
هذه الأنواع، نعم. وهناك العديد العديد من العوامل المسببة للمرض
that are present in these animals.
متواجدة في هذه الحيوانات.
These individuals are at specific risk,
هؤلاء الأشخاص معرضون لخطر معين،
particularly if there's blood contact, they're at risk for transmission
خصوصاً إذا كان هناك اتصال بالدم، فهم في خطر انتقال المرض
and possibly infection with novel viruses.
وربما عدوى الفيروسات.
Narrator: As the hunters display their kills, something surprising happens.
فيما يعرض الصيادون فرائسهم، يحدث أمر مثير للدهشة.
They show us filter paper they've used to collect the animals' blood.
إنهم يعطوننا أوراق الترشيح التي استعملوها لجمع دم الحيوانات.
The blood will be tested for zoonotic viruses,
وسيتم اختبار الدم للبحث عن الفيروسات الحيوانية المنشأ،
part of a program Dr. Wolfe has spent years setting up.
جزء من البرنامج الذي قام بإعداده د. وولف في سنوات.
NW: So this is from this animal right here,
هذه الورقة من هذا الحيوان هنا،
Greater Spot-Nosed Guenon.
قرد الGreater Spot-Nosed Guenon.
Every person who has one of those filter papers has at least,
كل شخص لديه واحدة من أوراق الترشيح تلك خضع على الأقل،
at a minimum, been through our basic health education
كحد أدنى، للتعليم الصحي الأساسي الخاص بنا
about the risks associated with these activities,
إزاء المخاطر المرتبطة بهذه الأنشطة،
which presumably, from our perspective,
وهو ما يفترض، من وجهة نظرنا،
gives them the ability to decrease their own risk,
أن يعطيهم القدرة على تقليل المخاطر المحيطة بهم،
and then obviously the risk to their families,
ومن ثم بالتأكيد تقليل المخاطر لعائلاتهم،
the village, the country, and the world.
والقرية، والبلد، والعالم.
NW: OK, before I continue, I think it's important to take just a moment
حسنا، قبل أن أواصل، أعتقد أنه من المهم أن نأخذ لحظة
to talk about bush meat. Bush meat is the hunting of wild game.
للحديث عن لحوم الطرائد. لحوم الطرائد هي لعبة الصيد البري.
OK? And you can consider all sorts of different bush meat.
صحيح؟ يمكنكم أن تأخذوا بالاعتبار جميع أنواع لحوم الطرائد المختلفة.
I'm going to be talking about this.
سأتحدث عن هذا.
When your children and grandchildren
عندما يطرح أبناؤكم وأحفادكم
sort of pose questions to you about this period of time,
أسئلة عن هذه الفترة من الزمن،
one of the things they're gonna ask you,
واحدة من الأشياء التي سوف يسألونكم عنها،
is how it was they we allowed some of our closest living relatives,
هي كيف سمحنا لبعض الكائنات الأقرب إلينا،
some of the most valuable and endangered species
بعض الأنواع الأكثر قيمة والمهددة بالانقراض
on our planet, to go extinct because we
على كوكبنا، بالانقراض لأننا
weren't able to address some of the issues
لم نكن قادرين على معالجة بعض قضايا
of poverty in these parts of the world.
الفقر في هذه المناطق من العالم.
But in fact that's not the only question they're going to ask you about this.
ولكن في الواقع هذا ليس السؤال الوحيد الذي سيطرحونه حول هذا الموضوع.
They're also going to ask you the question
السؤال الذي سيسألونكم هو
that when we knew that this was the way that HIV entered
أنه عندما كنا نعرف أن هذه هي الطريقة التي دخل فيروس HIV
into the human population,
في البشر،
and that other diseases had the potential to enter like this,
وغيرها من الأمراض التي يمكن أن تدخل مثل هذه،
why did we let these behaviors continue?
لماذا تركنا هذه السلوكيات تستمر؟
Why did we not find some other solution to this?
لماذا لم نجد أي حل آخر لهذا؟
They're going to say, in regions of profound
سيقولون، في المناطق التي تعاني
instability throughout the world,
من عدم الاستقرار في جميع أنحاء العالم،
where you have intense poverty, where populations are growing
حيث الفقر الشديد، والسكان يتزايدون
and you don't have sustainable resources like this,
وعدم توافر الموارد المستدامة كهذه،
this is going to lead to food insecurity.
سوف يؤدي ذلك إلى انعدام الأمن الغذائي.
But they're also going to ask you probably a different question.
ولكن سيطرحون سؤالاً مختلفاً ربما.
It's one that I think we all need to ask ourselves,
السؤال الذي في اعتقادي أنه علينا جميعا أن نسأل أنفسنا،
which is, why we thought the responsibility rested with this individual here.
وهو، لماذا كنا نعتقد أن المسؤولية تقع على عاتق هذا الشخص هنا.
Now this is the individual -- you can see just right up over his right shoulder --
الآن هذا هو الشخص - تستطيعون أن تروا ماذا يوجد فوق كتفه اليمنى -
this is the individual that hunted the monkey
هذا هو الشخص الذي اصطاد القرد
from the last picture that I showed you.
من الصورة السابقة التي عرضتها عليكم.
OK, take a look at his shirt.
حسناً، انظروا إلى قميصه.
You know, take a look at his face.
تعلمون، انظروا إلى وجهه.
Bush meat is one of the central crises,
لحوم الطرائد هي واحدة من الأزمات المركزية،
which is occurring in our population right now,
التي تحدث لمجتمعاتنا في الوقت الحالي،
in humanity, on this planet.
للبشرية، على هذا الكوكب.
But it can't be the fault of somebody like this.
ولكن لا يمكن أن تكون خطأ شخص مثل هذا.
OK? And solving it cannot be his responsibility alone.
صحيح؟ وحلها لا يمكن أن يكون مسؤوليته وحده.
There's no easy solutions,
ليست هناك حلول سهلة،
but what I'm saying to you is that we neglect this problem
ولكن ما أقوله لكم هو أننا أهملنا هذه المشكلة
at our own peril.
وهو ما يعرضنا للخطر.
So, in 1998, along with my mentors
في العام 1998، مع موجهيني
Don Burke and Colonel Mpoudi-Ngole,
دون بورك والعقيد مبودي نجوليه،
we went to actually start this work
ذهبنا لبدء هذا العمل فعلا
in Central Africa, to work with hunters
في وسط أفريقيا، للعمل مع الصيادين
in this part of the world.
في هذا الجزء من العالم.
And my job -- at that time I was a post-doctoral fellow,
وظيفتي -- في ذلك الوقت كنت زميل ما بعد الدكتوراه،
and I was really tasked with setting this up.
وكنت مكلفاً بالإعداد لهذا العمل.
So I said to myself, "OK, great --
فقلت لنفسي: "حسناً، عظيم
we're gonna collect all kinds of specimens. We're gonna go to all these
سنقوم بجمع كل أنواع العينات. سنذهب إلى جميع تلك
different locations. It's going to be wonderful."
المناطق المختلفة. سيكون رائعاً"
You know, I looked at the map; I picked out 17 sites;
كما تعلمون، نظرت إلى الخريطة، اخترت 17 مدينة،
I figured, no problem.
فقررت، لا مشكلة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Needless to say, I was drastically wrong.
غني عن القول، كنت على خطأ كبير.
This is challenging work to do.
هذا عمل فيه تحدٍ
Fortunately, I had and continue to have
لحسن الحظ، كان وما زال لدي
an absolutely wonderful team of colleagues and collaborators in my own team,
فريق رائع للغاية من الزملاء والمتعاونين في فريق العمل
and that's the only way that this work can really occur.
وهذه هي الطريقى الوحيدة التي يمكن لهذا العمل أن يحدث.
We have a whole range of challenges about this work.
لدينا مجموعة كاملة من التحديات حول هذا العمل.
One of them is just obtaining trust
واحد منهم فقط هو اكتساب الثقة
from individuals that we work with in the field.
من الأشخاص الذين نعمل معهم في الميدان.
The person you see on the right hand side is Paul DeLong-Minutu.
الشخص الذي تراه على الجانب الايمن هو بول ديلونغ مينوتو.
He's one of the best communicators that I've really ever dealt with.
هو أحد أفضل المتواصلين الذين تعاملت معهم في حياتي.
When I arrived I didn't speak a word of French,
عندما وصلت لم أكن أتكلم كلمة واحدة بالفرنسية،
and I still seemed to understand what it was he was saying.
وكان يبدو أنني أفهم ما كان يقوله.
Paul worked for years
عمل بول لسنوات
on the Cameroonian national radio and television,
في الاذاعة الوطنية الكاميرونية والتلفزيون،
and he spoke about health issues. He was a health correspondent.
وكان يتحدث عن القضايا الصحية. كان مراسلاً صحياً.
So we figured we'd hire this person -- when we got there he could
فرأينا أن نوظف هذا االشخص، عندما وصلنا إلى هناك
be a great communicator.
فبإمكانه أن يكون متواصلاً عظيما.
When we would get to these rural villages, though, what we found out
عندما وصلنا إلى تلك القرى الريفية، وجدنا
is that no one had television,
أن لا أحد يملك تلفازاً،
so they wouldn't recognize his face.
لذا لم يتعرفوا إليه.
But -- when he began to speak
ولكن - عندما بدأ الحديث
they would actually recognize his voice from the radio.
فقد تعرفوا على صوته من خلال الراديو.
And this was somebody who had incredible
وكان هذا الشخص لديه إمكانيات لا تصدق
potential to spread aspects of our message,
لنشر جوانب رسالتنا،
whether it be with regards to wildlife conservation
سواء كان ذلك يتعلق بحفظ الحياة البرية
or health prevention.
أو الوقاية الصحية.
Often we run into obstacles. This is us coming back from
كثيراً ما صادفتنا عقبات، نحن قادمون هنا من
one of these very rural sites,
من إحدى تلك المناطق النائية،
with specimens from 200 individuals
مع عينات مأخوذة من 200 شخص
that we needed to get back to the lab within 48 hours.
كنا بحاجة إلى أن نعود إلى المختبر في غضون 48 ساعة.
I like to show this shot -- this is
أريد أن أريكم هذه اللقطة - هذا هو
Ubald Tamoufe, who's the lead
أوبالد تاموفي، وهو المحقق
investigator in our Cameroon site.
الرئيسي في موقع الكاميرون لدينا.
Ubald laughs at me when I show this photo
يضحك أوبالد عندما أضع هذه الصورة
because of course you can't see his face.
لأنكم بالتأكيد لا يمكنكم أن تروا وجهه.
But the reason I like to show the shot
ولكن السبب في أنني أريد أن اريكم الصورة
is because you can see that he's about to solve this problem.
هو أنه يمكنكم رؤيته وهو على وشك حل هذه المشكلة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Which -- which he did, which he did.
وقد حل المشكلة.
Just a few quick before and after shots.
لقطات سريعة تعرض قبل وبعد
This was our laboratory before.
كان هذا مختبرنا سابقاً
This is what it looks like now.
وهذا ما يبدو عليه الآن.
Early on, in order to ship our specimens,
في وقت سابق، لكي نشحن عيناتنا،
we had to have dry ice. To get dry ice we had to go
كان علينا الحصول على الثلج الجاف. للحصول على الثلج الجاف كان يجب أن نذهب
to the breweries -- beg, borrow, steal to get these folks to give it to us.
إلى مصانع الجعة - نتسول، نقترض، نسرق لنجعل هؤلاء الناس يعطوننا إياه.
Now we have our own liquid nitrogen.
الآن لدينا النيتروجين السائل الخاص بنا.
I like to call our laboratory the coldest place in Central Africa -- it might be.
أود أن أسمي مختبرنا أبرد مكان في أفريقيا الوسطى - قد يكون.
And here's a shot of me, this is the before shot of me.
وهذه لقطة لي أنا، لقطة ما قبل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
No comment.
لا تعليق.
So what happened? So during the 10 years that we've been doing
ماذا حصل؟ خلال ال 10 سنوات التي كنا نقوم
this work, we actually surprised ourselves.
بهذا العمل، فاجأنا أنفسنا فعلا.
We made a number of discoveries.
حققنا عددا من الاكتشافات.
And what we've found is that if you look in the right place,
وما اكتشفناه هو انه اذا نظرتم في المكان المناسب،
you can actually monitor the flow
يمكنكم مراقبة تدفق
of these viruses into human populations.
هذه الفيروسات إلى البشر.
That gave us a tremendous amount of hope.
مما أعطانا قدراً هائلاً من الأمل.
What we've found is a whole range of new viruses in these individuals,
ما اكتشفناه هو مجموعة كاملة من الفيروسات الجديدة في هؤلاء الأفراد،
including new viruses in the same group
بما في ذلك فيروسات جديدة في نفس المجموعة
as HIV -- so, brand new retroviruses.
مثل فيروس HIV، لذا فيروسات ارتدادية جديدة.
And let's face it, any new retrovirus in the
ودعونا نواجه الأمر ، أي فيروسات ارتدادية جديدة في
human population -- it's something we should be aware of.
البشر - هو شيء ينبغي لنا أن نعلم عنه.
It's something we should be following. It's not something
شيء ينبغي لنا أن نتابعه. لا أن
that we should be surprised by.
نكون متفاجئين به.
Needless to say in the past
غني عن القول في الماضي
these viruses entering into these rural communities
هذه الفيروسات التي تدخل في هذه المجتمعات الريفية
might very well have gone extinct.
ربما انقرضت في الماضي بشكل جيد
That's no longer the case. Logging roads provide access to urban areas.
وهذا ليس موضوعنا. تسجيل الطرق يوفر مدخلاً للمدن.
And critically, what happens in central Africa
والأهم من ذلك، ما يحدث في افريقيا الوسطى
doesn't stay in Central Africa.
لا يبقى في أفريقيا الوسطى.
So, once we discovered that it was really possible
لذا، بعدما اكتشفنا أنه من الممكن حقاً
that we could actually do this monitoring,
أن نقوم بهذا الرصد،
we decided to move this from research, to
قررنا التحرك من هذا البحث، من أجل
really attempt to phase up to a global monitoring effort.
محاولة جادة للوصول إلى رصد الجهود حول العالم.
Through generous support and partnership
من خلال الدعم السخي والشراكة
scientifically with Google.org and the Skoll Foundation,
العلمية مع Google.org وSkoll Foundation،
we were able to start the Global Viral Forecasting Initiative
أصبحنا قادرين على بدء (المبادرة العالمية للتنبؤ الفيروسي)
and begin work in four different sites
وبدء العمل في أربعة مواقع مختلفة
in Africa and Asia.
في أفريقيا وآسيا.
Needless to say, different populations from different parts of the world
وغني عن القول، المجتمعات المختلفة من أنحاء مختلفة من العالم
have different sorts of contact.
لديها أنواع مختلفة من الاتصال.
So it's not just hunters in Central Africa.
فهذه المبادرة ليست مجرد صيادين من أفريقيا الوسطى.
It's also working in live animal markets --
انها تعمل أيضا في أسواق الحيوانات الحية --
these wet markets -- which is exactly the place where
تلك الأسواق الرطبة - التي هي بالضبط المكان الذي
SARS emerged in Asia.
نشأ فيه فيروس سارس في آسيا.
But really, this is just the beginning from our perspective.
ولكن في الحقيقة، هذه هي البداية فقط من وجهة نظرنا.
Our objective right now, in addition to
هدفنا الآن، بالإضافة إلى
deploying to these sites and getting everything moving,
الانتشار في هذه المواقع والعمل على تشغليها،
is to identify new partners
هو تحديد شركاء جدد
because we feel like this effort needs to be extended
لأننا نرى أن مثل هذا الجهد يحتاج إلى الانتشار
to probably 20 or more sites throughout the world -- to viral hotspots --
إلى ربما 20 موقع أو أكثر في جميع أنحاء العالم - إلى النقاط الساخنة الفيروسية -
because really the idea here is to cast an incredibly wide net
لأن الفكرة هنا هي إلقاء شبكة واسعة جداً
so that we can catch these things, ideally,
لكي نتمكن من التقاط هذه الأشياء، من الناحية المثالية،
before they make it to blood banks,
قبل وصولهم لبنوك الدم،
sexual networks, airplanes. And that's really our objective.
والعلاقات الجنسية، والطائرات، وهذا في الحقيقة هو هدفنا.
There was a time not very long ago
كان هناك زمن ليس ببعيد
when the discovery of unknown organisms
كان فيها اكتشاف كائنات غير معروفة
was something that held incredible awe for us.
شيء يثير الرعب فينا.
It had potential to really change the way that we saw ourselves,
وكان يمكن أن تغير الطريقة التي رأينا أنفسنا،
and thought about ourselves.
وفكرنا في أنفسنا.
Many people, I think, on our planet right now
أعتقد أن كثير من الناس على كوكبنا الآن،
despair, and they think
يئسوا، وهم يعتقدون
we've reached a point where we've discovered most of the things.
أننا لقد وصلنا إلى نقطة حيث عثرنا على معظم الأشياء.
I'm going tell you right now: please don't despair.
سأقولها لكم الآن: من فضلكم لا تيأسوا.
If an intelligent extra-terrestrial
إذا كلف شخص ذكي جدا
was taxed with writing the encyclopedia of life on our planet,
بكتابة موسوعة عن الحياة على كوكبنا،
27 out of 30 of these volumes
27 من أصل 30 جزء
would be devoted to bacteria and virus,
ستخصص للبكتيريا والفيروسات
with just a few of the volumes left
مع أجزاء قليلة فقط متبقية
for plants, fungus and animals,
للنباتات والفطريات والحيوانات --
humans being a footnote;
البشر في الحاشية --
interesting footnote but a footnote nonetheless.
حاشية مثيرة للاهتمام ولكنها مع ذلك في حاشية.
This is honestly the most exciting period
هذه هي بصراحة الفترة الأكثر إثارة
ever for the study of unknown life forms on our planet.
على الإطلاق لدراسة أشكال الحياة غير المعروفة على كوكبنا.
The dominant things that exist here
الأشياء المهيمنة التي توجد هنا
we know almost nothing about.
لا نعرف عنها أي شيء تقريباً.
And yet finally, we have the tools, which will allow us to actually explore that world
وأخيرا، لدينا الأدوات، التي سوف تمكننا من استكشاف ذلك العالم
and understand them.
وفهمه.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)